# BEN TOMHAVE, MS, CISSP

Herndon, VA • tomhave@secureconsulting.net • +1 703-282-8600

## TECHNICAL SECURITY ARCHITECT/LEADER

I am a well-regarded, highly experienced technical security professional with over 20 years of IT industry experience. As a security architect, I am a generalist who has served in nearly all types of security roles ranging from audit and assessment to incident response and forensics to security architecture and DevSecOps. I am currently seeking technical security leadership opportunities such as a security architect, security strategist, researcher, or similar. My most recent experiences include work in IAM and MFA, cloud security, container security, DevSecOps and application security practices, data security, security management, GRC and derivative use cases, policies and KPIs, vulnerability and patch management, system and network hardening, and overall enterprise security architecture.

**CORE COMPETENCIES:** Security architecture design and assessment (legacy and cloud); application security program management and DevSecOps; data security, data encryption, and enterprise key management; security management; identity and access management (IAM) strategy and architecture; governance, risk management, and compliance (GRC); security education, training, and awareness program development, management, and delivery, including a focus on behavioral information security; security product strategy and market analysis; analyst relations management.

## **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

Falcon's View Consulting, LLC

June 2015 to present

## **Principal**

As a solo consulting practice, providing cybersecurity professional services to multiple industries. Project work includes content development, security architecture, security product strategy and development, high-level security assessment and advisory services, specialized security training, and DevOps/DevSecOps architecture. Engagements include technical security ghost writing, program assessment based on NIST CSF, security advisory services on topics including risk management and container security, and general enterprise security architecture.

Pearson, Centennial, CO (remote)

September 2017 to April 2018

### **Manager, Security Engineering and Architecture**

Providing front-line management of a team of security engineers and architects responsible for identity and access management (IAM), multi-factor authentication (MFA), cloud security, container security, and data security (including encryption and certificate management). Provided technical leadership for the IAM and MFA initiative, including support for solution design and program communications. Technologies in-scope include ForgeRock, AWS, Cloud Custodian, CloudCheckr, CyberArk, and Vormetric.

New Context, San Francisco, CA (remote)

June 2016 to July 2017

### **Principal Security Scientist**

Served in a variable role performing research, product management of in-house development projects, and conducting business development. Efforts included creation of materials around the "Lean Security" methodology, development of presentations for conferences, and writing copy for sales collateral, blog posts, and byline articles. New Context has a focus on secure DevOps services and product development.

Ellucian, Fairfax, VA

October 2015 to June 2016

## **Manager, Information Security Architecture**

Evaluated current security processes, tools, and practices as a member of the information security team reporting directly to the CISO. Charged with evaluating the effectiveness of current solutions and identifying gaps in security protection. Developed a comprehensive security architecture framework to evaluate and manage security architecture strategy for both traditional on-premises and cloud environments. Worked with vendors and cross-organizationally to identify, evaluate, and test (pilot) solutions. Technologies evaluated

# BENJAMIN TOMHAVE, MS, CISSP

included data loss prevention (DLP), endpoint detection and response (EDR), traditional endpoint security, email security solutions (on-premises and Office 365), enterprise mobility management (EMM), network security tools and capabilities, identity and access management tools and capabilities, application security practices, cloud security tools (such as for AWS) and container (Docker) security tools. Technologies in-scope included AWS, Okta, Digital Guardian, IBM BigFix, Symantec EPP, Zscaler, Microsoft Adallom, FireEye, Splunk, Ansible, Rapid7, Tenable, CloudCheckr, StackRox, Jump Cloud, among many others.

K12, Inc., Herndon, VA

March 2015 to October 2015

## **Security Architect**

As a member of the enterprise architecture team, charged with broad responsibilities to inject security practices into the overall application stack. Reviewed overall environment and developed an incremental roadmap for addressing critical gaps and charting a progressive course to more effective enterprise security over time. Included collaborating with the team driving a DevOps initiative, as well as initiating changes to implement and leverage security operations automation.

Gartner, Inc., Arlington, VA (remote)

June 2013 to March 2015

#### **Research Director**

As a member of the Security & Risk Management Strategies team within Gartner for Technical Professionals, I conducted research into topics including risk management, security programs, security planning and management, application security, DLP, and SharePoint security. Additionally, I contributed content as a speaker at several Gartner and non-Gartner events and webinars, as well as delivering advisory services to clients and providing direct support to the sales team, both virtually and in-person, in multiple regions.

LockPath, Inc., Overland Park, KS (remote)

August 2011 to May 2013

## **Principal Consultant**

Hired to perform numerous duties as directed, including:

- **Professional Services:** Delivered consulting services supporting customer implementations of the Keylight platform and suite of applications.
- **Customer Training:** Developed and delivered comprehensive customer training across all LockPath products. Curriculum was tailored to multiple learner styles, including use of visual, auditory, and tactile techniques.
- **Writing:** Produced multiple written pieces, including byline articles and white papers, ranging in length from a few hundred to a couple thousand words.
- **Public Speaking:** Delivered presentations at several security-related conferences, including the RSA USA Conference, Secure360, the Rocky Mountain Information Security Conference (RMISC), the ISC<sup>2</sup> Security Congress, and the ISSA International Conference.
- **Partner Enablement:** Worked with partners to ensure that they were well supported and able to fulfill their mission requirements as pertained to delivering services related to LockPath products.
- Other Duties as Assigned: Completed other activities as assigned, including performing market analysis, providing input on product design discussions, and assisting with security policy development.

Gemini Security Solutions, Chantilly, VA

May 2010 to August 2011

## Sr. Security Analyst, Business Development Management

Experienced consultant hired to develop business relationships and grow client-base. Contributed to billable projects, development of proposals and statements of work, and promotion of the company. Increased company profile through writing and speaking engagements. Provided subject matter expertise in core competencies for use on client projects, internal consulting, contributing to industry groups and initiatives, and overall knowledge development and transfer.

# BENJAMIN L. TOMHAVE, MS, CISSP

Independent - Various, Fairfax, VA

December 2009 to May 2010

## Consultant / Author / Speaker

Worked through a variety of sources to provide security professional services to clients. Engagements and expertise include security and risk assessment, policy development, security program development and management, encryption key management, and secure application development. Client organizations have ranged in size from small to larger.

Foreground Security, Fairfax, VA

October 2009 to December 2009

### **Senior Security Engineer**

Team lead for implementation and project management of a complete security infrastructure upgrade for a large civilian government agency. Helped manage deployment of SIEM, NIDS, HIDS, FISMA tool, and network monitoring tool. Utilized products from Nitro Security, Trend Micro (formerly Third Brigade), Relational Security, and NetWitness.

Highwinds, Phoenix, AZ

January - September 2009

## **Technical Director of Information Security & Compliance**

Recruited to serve as the first full-time security resource for the organization. Objectives included shepherding Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard (PCI DSS) compliance efforts for one Level 2 and two Level 3 merchants. Activities included addressing policy development, data cleanup, security scanning and testing, incident response management, network security, logging and monitoring, identity and access management, training and awareness, and application security.

BT Professional Services, Reston, Virginia

2007 - 2009

## **Senior Security Consultant**

Recruited to serve as a regional security practice lead to assist with the development, qualification, and execution of client opportunities. Led and participated in information security consulting engagements covering the full spectrum of information security, information security management, business consulting, information assurance, risk and compliance, and governance. Developed and delivered internal training programs that enhanced internal capabilities to support and promote the security portfolio. Provided pre-sales support for security-related engagements.

AOL, LLC, Dulles, Virginia

2003 - 2007

### **Senior Technical Security Engineer**

Recruited as an individual contributor for a joint incident response management and security assurance team. Developed the position to take lead responsibilities for information security management, including security assurance, and the training and awareness program. The success of the information security management program, which was later separate from incident response management, resulted in a marked decrease in security incidents and an overall improvement in enterprise risk resiliency.

Additional experience prior to 2003. Details available upon request.

#### **EDUCATION AND CREDENTIALS**

## Master of Science Degree in Engineering Management

Concentration: Information Security Management
The George Washington University – Washington, District of Columbia

**Bachelor of Arts Degree in Computer Science** 

LUTHER COLLEGE - Decorah, Iowa

# BENJAMIN TOMHAVE, MS, CISSP

### **Professional Certifications**

CISSP - Certified Information Systems Security Professional #46697

## **Papers & Publications**

Please See: http://secureconsulting.net/papers-publications.html

## PROFESSIONAL TRAINING AND CONFERENCES

AWS: Cloud Practitioner Essentials, Security Fundamentals Online, Well-Architected Training BJ Fogg Behavior Design Boot Camp (2017)

RSA Conference USA 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

Rocky Mountain Information Security Conference 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

MISTI InfoSec World (2017), Cloud Security World (2016), Cybersecurity World (2015)

ISSA International Conference 2010, 2011, 2012, 2017

Secure 360 2011, 2012, 2013

ISC<sup>2</sup> Security Congress 2012

Society of Information Risk Analysts Conference (SIRAcon) 2012

NESCO Town Hall: Security Risk Management Practices for Electric Utilities (May 2012)

OWASP AppSec USA (2010), AppSec DC (2010), Summit (2011)

Security B-Sides – Attendee: Las Vegas (2009, 2015), San Francisco (2010)

Security B-Sides – Austin (Organizer/Co-Founder, 2010, 2011), Ottawa (2010)

EnergySec Summit 2010

Cyber Information Security Conference (CIScon) 2009

BlackHat USA Conference 2009

ISACA Information Security Management Conference 2005, 2006

NRA Range Safety Officer (2013)

NSA INFOSEC Assessment Methodology (IAM) Training (2006)

NSA INFOSEC Evaluation Methodology (IEM) Training (2006)

BSi ISO 17799 Implementation (2005)

"Facilitative Leadership" by Interaction Associates (2007)

"Managing Conflict" by Ridge Associates (2005)

"Intercultural Training: Working with Indian Nationals" by Prudential Financial (2007)

SANS Track 8: System Forensics, Investigations, and Response (2004)

## **PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS**

Senior Member - Information Systems Security Association

Previous Affiliations

Former Member – American Bar Association Information Security Committee

Former Member - American Bar Association eDiscovery and Digital Evidence Committee

Former Member - OASIS EKMI and KMIP Technical Committees

Former Member – Open Web Application Security Program (OWASP) and OWASP Global Conferences Committee Former Board Member – OWASP Northern Virginia (NoVA) Chapter

Former Contributing Author / Core Guide (Practical Security) - Truth to Power Association

Former Member – SANS Technology Institute Strategic Planning Advisory Committee

Former Board Member - Society of Information Risk Analysts

Former Co-Chair - American Bar Association Information Security Committee